Guide to the John Ruskin Letters to Ellen Heaton
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
John Ruskin Letters to Ellen Heaton
1850-1864
1855-1864
MSS 46
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
.42
1 box
The collection comprises letters from John Ruskin to Ellen Heaton, written from 1855 to 1864.
Ruskin, John, 1819-1900
Biographical / Historical
John Ruskin (1819-1900) was a British art and architectural critic, social commentator, educator, and artist. Born in London to wealthy Scottish parents, Ruskin began drawing lessons at a young age. After completing his studies at Oxford, Ruskin traveled extensively in Europe, where he would develop a special interest in Italy, later inspiring some of his best known written works, including The Stones of Venice. Ruskin was an influential supporter of the artist J.M.W. Turner, as well as a major influence on the group known as the Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood. The Pre-Raphaelites sought to reform British art through a return to honest simplicity and the use of luminous colors and literary themes. Ruskin and the Pre-Raphaelites advocated a certain "truth to nature," emphasizing that many layers of truth, especially regarding nature, may be ascertained through direct observation. His many publications included The Seven Lamps of Architecture (1849), The Elements of Drawing (1857), and Modern Painters (five volumes, 1843-1860). In addition to art and architecture criticism and history, Ruskin's writings ranged in theme from social issues, education, geology, natural history, and political economy.
The recipient of the letters, Ellen Heaton (1816-1894), was a Leeds based art collector and philanthropist. Heaton began collecting art after inheriting a significant amount of money and property following the deaths of her parents. It is unclear how Ruskin and Heaton first met, but the earliest surviving correspondence suggests that Heaton may have contacted Ruskin for advice about a group of Turner drawings she was considering for purchase after reading the early volumes of Modern Painters. The introduction likely came through Thomas Richmond. Over the course of their friendship, Heaton frequently solicited art collecting advice from Ruskin, who appears to have sometimes facilitated sales for her, or purchased items on her behalf. Heaton was among the first to commission work by the painter Dante Gabriel Rossetti. Ruskin also encouraged her to support artists such as Arthur Hughes, J.W. Inchbold, and Edward Burne-Jones (though Heaton declined to purchase any work by Burne-Jones). Ruskin discouraged her initial interest in Ford Maddox Brown.
Heaton was often referred to as having had a unique personality. In an 1863 letter to his father, Ruskin wrote, "Miss Heaton is—Miss Heaton, and always will be—" ( Sublime and Instructive, 151). Heaton was friendly with a number of writers and artists of her era, including Elizabeth Barrett Browning and Robert Browning. Heaton never married. She traveled extensively throughout Great Britain and the continent, often with her domestic partner, Fanny Haworth. In addition to her direct support of artists through commissioned paintings and drawings, Heaton also engaged in acts of cultural philanthropy, including providing the financial means for working men to attend lectures and supporting impoverished lace artisans in Leeds.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series: I. Letters from John Ruskin to Ellen Heaton; II. Miscellaneous. The letters are arranged chronologically. Item numbering corresponds to the numbering in Surteees, Sublime & instructive.
Existence and Location of Copies
The letters are transcribed in their entirety, with annotations, in: Sublime & instructive: letters from John Ruskin to Louisa, Marchioness of Waterford, Anna Blunden and Ellen Heaton. Edited by Virginia Surtees. London: Michael Joseph, [1972].
See: http://hdl.handle.net/10079/bibid/579348
Related Materials
Related material: Dante Gabriel Rossetti Letters to Ellen Heaton (MSS 47), Yale Center for British Art, Department of Rare Books and Manuscripts.
Custodial History
The material passed from Ellen Heaton to her nephew John Heaton, and subsequently to his brother Beresford Heaton, then to Katherine Ogilvy Heaton, and finally to Elizabeth Maud Sackville Robertson. Sold at auction, Christie, Manson & Woods, July 16, 1969 (see catalog entry no. 117).
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises 90 items, including 86 letters from John Ruskin to Ellen Heaton written from 1855 to 1864 (the bulk from 1855 to 1857). Ruskin's letters take on a mentoring tone toward Heaton and are often full of advice, primarily related to artistic practice and collecting. Heaton was an avid art collector and often seems to have solicited Ruskin's opinions on works prior to purchase. The letters reflect Ruskin's role in shaping the larger British art market and community, according to his particular taste and philosophies. Ruskin and Heaton shared a particular interest in the drawings of J.M.W. Turner, and the acquisition, care, exhibition, and appreciation of these works are frequently addressed in the letters. Ruskin writes: "For money's worth, & enjoyment to yourself, (at least I hope so as you gain more knowledge) an inch of Turner is worth an acre of other people – there is no comparison possible between him and any body else in landscape. Only in buying Turner – you now do no good to art whatsoever – only to yourself" (letter H.12, May 19, 1855).
Ruskin demonstrates an intimate knowledge of Heaton's collection and appears to have occasionally handled art market transactions on Heaton's behalf, just as Heaton appears to have purchased particular pieces on Ruskin's request. He writes frequently of borrowing or consulting works in her collection, and sometimes suggests methods for framing and storing particular objects.
Ruskin's advice for Heaton, however, often reaches beyond the physical presence of artworks. His letters are rich in their explications of tactics for looking at works of art, particularly landscapes. The letters provide some insight into Ruskin's writing process, particularly in regards to his monumental work Modern Painters. Occasionally Heaton shares some of her own writing, apparently collections of moral tales, about which Ruskin provides feedback regarding writing style and technique.
In 1855, Ruskin refers continually to Dante Gabriel Rossetti, who worked on subjects from Dante Alighieri for Ruskin and Heaton. Neither Heaton nor Ruskin are entirely happy with the work: "The Rachel [i.e. Rossetti's Rachel and Leah] is a curious instance of the danger of interfering with R. I wanted some illustrations from Dante for myself … he didn't do any of them for a long time, until I got provoked & said I thought it was very bad of him – and then he did this. He never would fail in a subject of his own choice" (letter H.23, mid-November, 1855).
A number of letters refer to the artist and model Elizabeth Siddall. Ruskin writes: "By the bye there is one of Rossetti's pupils, a poor girl, dying I am afraid, of ineffable genius, to whom some day … a commission may … be charity, but there is no hurry, as she doesn't work well enough yet, and Rossetti and I will take care of her till she does, if she lives" (letter H.6, February 1855).
The quotidian details of the letters touch upon Ruskin's travels, social visits, speaking obligations, and states of health. These details provide glimpses of the activities of Britain's intellectual society. Several letters address Heaton's acquisition, on Ruskin's behalf, of photographs depicting particular landscapes and works of art, shedding light on the role photography played in Ruskin's artistic and intellectual processes, whether as reference material, documentation, or works unto themselves.
The series of Miscellaneous material comprises four items, including two letters from Ruskin to Thomas Richmond, a page of quotations of Biblical verse, and a note from Heaton (to her family) on the preservation or publication of these letters, in commemoration of Ruskin.
Art; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art appreciation; Painters -- Great Britain; Painting -- Conservation and restoration; Painting, British -- 19th century; Photography; Rhetoric; Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 ( Modern painters); Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Brown, Ford Madox, 1821-1893; Browning, Elizabeth Barrett, 1806-1861; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321; Durham, Joseph, 1814-1877; Griffith, Thomas, active 1831-1869; Hughes, Arthur, 1832-1915; Hunt, William Holman, 1827-1910; Inchbold, John William, 1830-1888; Ramsden, John William; Richmond, Thomas, 1802-1874; Siddall, Elizabeth; White, David Thomas; Art Treasures Exhibition ( 1857 Manchester, England); Bolton Abbey (Bolton Abbey, England); Leeds Philosophical and Literary Society; Old Water-Colour Society (London, England); Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood
- Letters from John Ruskin to Ellen Heaton, Ruskin, John, 1819-1900
  Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 February 3; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.1)
    Scope and Contents
    Ruskin advises Heaton on the market for drawings by J.M.W. Turner, recommending "the Walls of Rome or Parnassus as the sweetest drawings."
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Walls of Rome with the Tomb of Caius Sestus; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Parnassus and Castalian Spring; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 February 5; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.2)
    Ruskin notifies Heaton that he has acquired (for Heaton) Turner's Berne and his Waterloo, for 50 guineas each. "I think you will like better to look at the sweet river and the cloudy Alps than at the dead bodies of soldiers in the firelight." He conjectures that the Parnassus or Walls of Rome might be had for a similar price. Mentions Ruskin's Examples of the architecture of Venice.
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Bernese Alps; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Field of Waterloo; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Parnassus and Castalian Spring; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Walls of Rome with the Tomb of Caius Sestus; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Examples of the architecture of Venice; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 February 9; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.3)
    Ruskin has acquired Turner's Walls of Rome for Heaton, having "no hesitation in ranking this as among the nine or ten best vignettes which Turner ever executed." Ruskin comments on the qualities of the Walls of Rome and of the Berne. He recommends at once "to have these two vignettes framed so as not to touch the glass -- and pasted in at back to keep out Leeds smoke. The least yellowing in the Caius Cestius would be fatal." Ruskin praises the poetry of Elizabeth Barrett Browning.
    Picture frames and framing; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Bernese Alps; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Walls of Rome with the Tomb of Caius Sestus; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Browning, Elizabeth Barrett, 1806-1861; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 February 12?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.4)
    "I write in great haste to tell you to be sure not to have the pasteboard on which the vignettes are drawn, cut, as you would much diminish their market value by doing so … whatever you do -- do yourself -- on no account let them out of your house, or into the hands of any mounter or framemaker whatsoever."
    Picture frames and framing; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 mid-February?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 25 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder H.5)
    Ruskin writes that he cannot advise Heaton on matters of framing, as he has "never yet framed a picture to [his] liking." He offers further praise of Turner's Walls of Rome. He advises against the purchase of his "Venice folios." He concludes: "I am sorry to say I mean't & mean what I say of art to separate it from other pursuits. Music helps religious feelings in thousands. Politics ... are a part of Religion. Pictorial art is too often separated from it -- or opposed to it." [Date provided by Surtees: ? Mid-February 1855]
    Picture frames and framing; Art; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Walls of Rome with the Tomb of Caius Sestus; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 February?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter; 20 x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder H.6)
    Ruskin explains that he has not been able to get some photographs he desires. He advises Heaton that her friend may wish to commission work from Arthur Hughes, promising to send Heaton Hughes's address and suggesting that she keep him in mind for any future purchases. Ruskin recommends commissioning work from "one of Rossettis pupils -- a poor girl -- dying I am afraid -- of ineffable genius" [though unnamed in the letter, this is Elizabeth Eleanor Siddall] but that "there is no hurry as she don't [sic] work well enough yet."
    Hughes, Arthur, 1832-1915; Siddall, Elizabeth; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 March 4?; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 21 x 25 cm, folded to 21 x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder H.7)
    Ruskin expresses his sympathy for Elizabeth Barrett Browning, who is ill. Ruskin informs Heaton he will send her photographs which are to be copied in sepia, chalk or pencil "as if they were nature itself." Ruskin argues, against the "Masters", that this practice "will do more for a pupil than a years common teaching." Ruskin praises Turner's use of space and drawing of form, praising Walls of Rome as a better work than his Berne. In a postscript, Ruskin states that "men who are not painters" do not get as much good out of art as they do out of "other divine things.".
    Art -- Reproduction; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Bernese Alps; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Walls of Rome with the Tomb of Caius Sestus; Browning, Elizabeth Barrett, 1806-1861; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 March?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.8)
    Ruskin remarks that it is necessary to devote time to art appreciation, noting that Heaton initially liked the sky of Turner's Berne which Ruskin states is "exactly the worst part of the drawing." Ruskin declares Caius Cestius "the finer vignette." Ruskin refers to "Mr Durham" (Joseph Durham, who sculpted a portrait bust of Heaton) but confesses that he doesn't "much care about sculpture."
    Art appreciation; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Bernese Alps; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Walls of Rome with the Tomb of Caius Sestus; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Durham, Joseph, 1814-1877; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 May 9; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.9)
    Ruskin apologizes that he will not be able to meet Heaton the following morning and says that she may see the pictures and sketches she is interested in if she visits his house in the afternoon instead. Ruskin professes his dismay that he has not been able to talk much with Heaton recently but encourages her to ask him "anything and everything.". Ruskin states that his address for the foreseeable future will be the Calverley Hotel, Tunbridge Wells. Ruskin has bought Heaton another photograph which he will have sent by bearer. [Date provided by Surtees: 9 May 1855]
    Photography; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 May 11; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 20 x 25 cm, folded to 20 x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder H.10)
    "I hope to call tomorrow about 3 o'clock & to bring calotypes with me … I had your kind note -- but my endeavours were notwithstanding this ... vain, for the present chiefly because we cannot get the permanence of photography ascertained. I will tell you more tomorrow." [Date given by postmark: 11 May 1855]
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 May 19?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.11)
    Ruskin is writing from his bed. He advises Heaton to acquire a Turner, remarking that Turner's Parnassus and Castle St Angelo is better than his Berne, with the Parnassus the "finest." Ruskin advises Heaton to protect the Parnassus from light. He suggests she commissions work from both John William Inchbold and Arthur Hughes. He admits he has not been able to get Heaton's daguerreotypes but suggests places where she might be able to source duplicates or alternatives. Ruskin admits that he is "quite laid up" and enquires after Thomas Richmond's health. In a postscript, Ruskin praises Hughes's use of colour and compliments Heaton's perception of colour. [Date provided by Surtees: 19? May 1855]
    Photography; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Bernese Alps; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Parnassus and Castalian Spring; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Castle of St Angelo; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Inchbold, John William, 1830-1888; Hughes, Arthur, 1832-1915; Richmond, Thomas, 1802-1874; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 May; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.12)
    Ruskin expresses his distaste that David Thomas White (art dealer) has offered Turner's Parnassus to Heaton for a price higher than the 50 guineas he offered to Ruskin. Ruskin tells Heaton to mention to White that she knows that White gave Ruskin a better price because "he will come down immediately." Ruskin says that White showed him Richmond's Alborough but that he doesn't care for it. [Date provided by Surtees: May 1855]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Parnassus and Castalian Spring; White, David Thomas; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Richmond, Thomas, 1802-1874; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 May; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.13)
    Ruskin advises Heaton to give White £5 for Turner's Castle St Angelo or offer White both her vignettes and £60 for larger drawings (he recommends either Turner's Salisbury or Ingleborough ). If Heaton wants to keep her vignettes, Ruskin suggests that she "try to get the Parnassus with your other two - say 55 for it - but not more.". [Date provided by Surtees: May 1855]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Castle of St Angelo; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Parnassus and Castalian Spring; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; White, David Thomas; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 May?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.14)
    Ruskin advises Heaton that if she can get Turner's Berne for £40, she should. He asks her for the £5 she promised to the Arundel Society but says that if this will make it difficult for her to buy the Berne, Ruskin will pay the £5 and Heaton can reimburse him later. He says that he is glad that she bought Turner's Parnassus which he praises liberally. Ruskin states he has nearly recovered from his illness and that he is happy to hear that Thomas Richmond is similarly improving. [Date provided by Surtees: c. May 1855]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Bernese Alps; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Parnassus and Castalian Spring; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; White, David Thomas; Arundel Society for Promoting the Knowledge of Art; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 early June?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.15)
    "There is no other vignette comparable to those you have -- the Pisa & Bacharach are both inferior -- Keep what you have, & be proud and thankful. Many thanks & sincere ones for help with Arundel." [Date provided by Surtees: ? Early June 1885]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Santa Maria della Spina, Pisa; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Bacharach on the Rhine; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 summer?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.16)
    "I have seen neither of the pictures & fear I cannot see them at present -- but you cannot be wrong in taking whichever Hughes himself recommends. -- I have some more photographs for you -- Shall I send them to Leeds?" [Date provided by Surtees: Summer 1855]
    Hughes, Arthur, 1832-1915; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 October?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 11 cm (Box 1, Folder H.17)